A Finding Aid to the Charles Ramsburg papers, 1959-2020, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Charles Ramsburg papers
1959-2020
Archives of American Art
Ramsburg, Charles
AAA.ramschar
Archival Resource Key
0.8 Linear feet
6.04 Gigabytes
The papers of artist Charles Ramsburg (1942- ) measure 0.8 linear feet and 6.04 GB, and date from 1959-2020. The collection documents Ramsburg's career and art practice through biographical material, correspondence, exhibition files, printed material, and photographic material. Some email correspondence, three video recordings and the bulk of the photographs are in digital form.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Ramsburg (1942- ) is an artist in New York City who creates sculptures and drawings related to the minutiae of nature. Originally from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, Ramsburg studied at the San Francisco Art Institute, University of Arizona, and University of California at Santa Barbara. He moved to New Mexico in 1970, and after several decades returned to the east coast. Ramsburg's work has been featured in exhibitions internationally, and he has been represented by Carter Burden Gallery in New York and Horwitch LewAllen Gallery in New Mexico.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Archives of American Art by Charles Ramsburg in 2017, 2019 and 2020.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as five series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1959-circa 1993 (Box 1, 1 folder; ER06, ER09, 0.162 GB)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1961-2019 (Box 1, 2 folders; ER07-ER08, 0.054 GB)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1989-2005 (Box 1, 0.3 linear feet; ER01, 3.86 GB)
Series 4: Printed Material, circa 1980-2018 (Box 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographic Material, 1990-2017 (Box 2, 0.2 linear feet; ER02-ER05, 1.94 GB)
Scope and Contents
The papers of artist Charles Ramsburg (1942- ) measure 0.8 linear feet and 6.04 GB, and date from 1959-2020. The collection documents Ramsburg's career and art practice through biographical material, correspondence, exhibition files, printed material, and photographic material. Some email correspondence, three video recordings and the bulk of the photographs are in digital form.
Artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Video recordings
- Biographical Material, 1959-2020; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder Box 1; 0.162 Gigabytes ER06, ER09
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes a "talent test" completed by Ramsburg, an artist's statement, and photocopy of a cartoon. Also included is a promotional digital video recording for Carter Burden Network featuring Ramsburg at the Carter Burden Gallery and a profile video, part of an artist portrait series for Carter Burden Gallery by Anahita Amirshahi.
  - Biographical Material, 1959-circa 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Carter Burden Network (Carter Burden Gallery) 2017 Promotional Video, Digital Video Recording, Archival Resource Key; 0.05 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER06)
  - A Portrait of Charles Ramsburg, film by Anahita Amirshahi (2020), Digital Video Recording, Archival Resource Key; 0.112 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER09)
- Correspondence, 1961-2020; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 1; 0.054 Gigabytes ER07-ER08
  Correspondence includes letters and printed emails to and from friends, art dealers, and collectors. Also includes some email correspondence in digital form.
  - Correspondence, 1961-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2013-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Email Correspondence, Digital Documents, 2018-2019; Archival Resource Key; 0.012 Gigabytes 93 computer files (Folder ER07)
  - Email Correspondence, Digital Documents and Photographs, 2020; Archival Resource Key; 0.042 Gigabytes 88 computer files (Folder ER08)
- Exhibition Files, 1989-2005; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1; 3.86 Gigabytes ER01
  Exhibition files contain price lists, consignment agreements, correspondence, sales records, resumes, announcements, clippings, and one digital video recording documenting the exhibition at Chaos Gallery in Serbia. Dialogue in the video recording is in Serbian.
  - Allene Lapides Gallery, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Horwitch LewAllen Gallery, 1993-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Budapesti Töréneti Múzeum, 1995-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chaos Gallery, 2001-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes born-digital file, see ER01
  - Chaos Gallery, Digital Video Recording, 2005; Archival Resource Key; 3.86 Gigabytes 1 computer file (Folder ER01)
- Printed Material, circa 1980-2018; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material includes exhibition announcements and catalogs, clippings of reviews of Ramsburg's work, and four self-published books of artwork.
  - Announcements, circa 1980-2018; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Catalogs, circa 1980-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, circa 1985-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Self-published Books, 2010-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographic Material, 1990-2017; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2; 1.94 Gigabytes ER02-ER05
  Photographic material consists of prints, slides, transparencies and digital images of Ramsburg's artwork, including his Icons of Nature and Pathing Sticks series.
  - Prints, Slides, and Transparencies of Artwork, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Shield Series, Lit. Icons, Mixed Media Sculpture, Metal Sculpture," Digital Photographs, 2006; Archival Resource Key; 0.528 Gigabytes 276 computer files (Folder ER02)
  - Icons of Nature, Walking Stick, and Pathing Stick Series, Digital Photographs, 2006-2013; Archival Resource Key; 0.891 Gigabytes 741 computer files (Folder ER03)
  - "Drawings, ICE," Digital Photographs, 2010; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Gigabytes 10 computer files (Folder ER04)
  - Shadow Drawings, Digital Photographs, 2015-2017; Archival Resource Key; 0.03 Gigabytes 21 computer files (Folder ER05)